Contact

nishthaa.madaan@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/nishtha-madaan-21017541 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Machine Learning
Natural Language Processing
Artificial Intelligence (AI)

Certifications

Deep Learning Specialization Sequence Models Convolutional Neural Networks

Structuring Machine Learning Projects

Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization

Honors-Awards

Dean's Merit List Awardee

Research Award

Second Prize at COMAD 2015 Data Challenge

VAST Challenge 2013 : Prediction of Movie Reviews and Earning

IBM Academia Recognition Award

Publications

A System for Predicting Health of an e-Contract

Extracting Temporal Relations from Dependency Trees using Edge Embeddings

Cognitive Compliance for Financial Regulations

Visual Exploration of Regulatory Documents

Analyze, Detect and Remove Gender Stereotyping from Bollywood Movies

Nishtha Madaan

IBM Research AI | Global Top 100 Women in AI Ethics Delhi

Summary

I work as an Advisory Researcher at IBM Research India. I primarily work on Data for AI, Fairness and Algorithmic Bias. My job responsibility includes designing and developing NLP and Machine Learning based solutions for businesses. I have also been leading multiple academic research collaborations and have mentored ~30+ students. My work has been covered by leading newspapers, blogs and also featured in MIT Technology Review. I have co-authored several research papers published in renowned computer science journals and conferences. I have delivered many talks and guest lectures at national and international venues like IIITD, VIT Amravati, Northcap University, DTU Delhi, EPFL Switzerland, GHCI Bangalore, FES Berlin, NUS Singapore etc.

For any questions/ concerns, write to me at nishthamadaan@in.ibm.com.

Experience

IBM Research Al 5 years 3 months

Advisory Research Engineer
June 2019 - Present (1 year 3 months)

New Delhi Area, India

I am working on building AI solutions which are more Trusted especially in Text.

Staff Research Engineer
April 2017 - June 2019 (2 years 3 months)

New Delhi Area, India

I had been driving work towards AI Ethics. The work primarily involved building models on structured and unstructured data using Deep Learning. I was recognised as 1 among Top 100 Women in AI Ethics in 2019. Also, I have been mentoring few students from different academic institutes to co-create technologies in the area.

Also I had been a part of Cognitive Contracts effort in which we were working on building solutions to extract key features from a textual contract document. The work involved extensive amount of NLP and ML.

Research Software Engineer
June 2015 - April 2017 (1 year 11 months)
New Delhi Area, India

I work in Cognitive Finance Team at IBM Research, New Delhi which is a part of Knowledge Engineering Department. My core research interests include Natural Language Processing, Graph Mining and Machine Learning. I primarily work on unstructured and structured text.

At IBM, I am working on Financial Documents. The project involves building models for unstructured data using Text Mining and Deep Learning.

Parallely, I am working on projects related to bias (gender bias and persuasive bias) in text which involves building reasoning algorithms to ensure fairness.

Also, I am working on a couple of research problems around knowledge representation and summarization in financial documents using NLP and DL.

IIIT Hyderabad
Teaching Assistant
August 2014 - December 2014 (5 months)
Introduction to Databases

Progress Software Summer Research Intern May 2014 - July 2014 (3 months) Hyderabad Area, India

Worked on building a Recommendation System using hadoop and hbase.

EnhanceEdu Research Assistant January 2014 - July 2014 (7 months)

Education

IIIT Hyderabad

BTech + MS by research in Computer Science, NLP, ML

University of Vienna

Diploma Degree in Enterprise Modelling, Computer Science · (2015 - 2015)